{
  "reference_number": "643",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We need a target to be reached by 2050 or before, not in the second half of the century. The Climate Change Commission needs to\n advise on the targets within each emission budget to get there, and also how to get there in a way which encourages a growth\n economy and investment in new technologies. The ETS should not be the only tool used to get there. We want genuine changes in\n\n all sectors to get there."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "New Zero Emissions without a doubt. The agriculture sector needs to be included, as this will hopefully also encourage a change in\n mindset away from business as usual where technology is used to making farming less intensive, with a higher quality product which\n\n in the long term will have less impact on our environment."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Yes, there is a place for the ETS as part of us meeting our goals, but this should be a secondary option. We should actively reduce\n our emissions, then use the ETS as a supplementary tool. As the ETS does not have a good history, it needs sorting out. It needs to\n\n be transparent and simple so history does not repeat itself. I also believe the ETS should not be in the first emissions target, but\n should be used to target the GHG emissions which are tricky to reduce after all sectors have made an honest effort of reducing their\n carbon emissions to as low as possible."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. We should set short term targets between now and 2050 (say 5 - 10 years). If we miss the 10 year target, then then 20 year\n target will need to increase. This should be in no way used to reduce our targets if we are finding it too difficult or as a way to give in\n to some sectors kicking up a fuss."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I feel that we should have a plan in place to meet our 2050 target from the start, even if it needs adjusting. Without a long term plan\n we are making things more difficult for ourselves. For example the emissions budgets set in 2025 and 2030 (figure 2) to be put in\n\n place now."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Yes. Definitely with the Climate Change Commission's advice though and not to be adjusted by each government for their own\nbenefit."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I believe the first and second budget (so the emission budgets commencing in 2020 and 2025 in figure 2 should be set in place, and\n\nonly the third on wards emission budget be able to be changed. This prevents the govt. making changes to the emissions budgets\nto benefit themselves."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, this appears to be a holistic approach which is what is required. The Climate Change Commission also needs to work as an\nintegrated team so all of these considerations are looked at together, not independently of one another."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, change has to happen now!!! Even 2020 is too far away in my mind for changes to start happening. Some of the 'low hanging\nfruit' could be targeted as soon as the bill comes into place."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The advice of the Climate Change Commission, keep the public consultation lines open. Industry leaders should have to put forward\n\ntheir ideas for how their sector will reduce its carbon emissions for the Climate Change Commission to take into account when it\nadvises the govt."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I believe the Climate Change Commissioning should also hold the govt. accountable to prevent the govt. making decisions for their\n\nown benefit (e.g. winning votes, or keeping certain sectors happy). Obviously our international declaration to the Paris agreement\nholds us accountable as well, but we need a body of experts closer to home also keeping the govt. accountable day to day."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "As I have said earlier, this should not be the main way that we reach our targets though. But yes, most definitely, an independent\nClimate Change Commission needs to advise the govt."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, the more holistic the better. If all Kiwis know that someone in the Climate Change Commission is able to speak on behalf of\n\nthem, they will likely be more supportive and proactive when it comes to making changes which will effect them personally(or as a\nbusiness) to help us reach our targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Most definitely. As we are already having to adapt, this needs to be included in the same Bill so the link between reducing GHG\nemissions and the effect that climate change is already having on people and companies stays well connected. If there becomes a\n\ndisconnect, this is when people may become disheartened ."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. The review of the adaption plan will need to be continuous as the effects of climate change are someone unpredictable,\nespecially the time frame in which aspects of the adaption plan will need to come into effect."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "A targeted adaption reporting power should be mandatory for all companies over a certain size in New Zealand. Companies should\nhave to report their risk and adaptation plans publicly as this will create a community of ideas and also inspire other companies on\n\nhow they can adapt to climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "On a personal note, I am a Building Scientist (I make buildings more energy efficient as a tool for mitigating climate change) and I have\n\njust had my role made redundant due to the large engineering firm no longer seeing any work in this area. This is really upsetting as\nwe know NZ's building stock needs serious assistance to become healthier and more energy efficient, and that there needs to be\n\ndrastic changed for NZ to reach its emissions targets - yet there is no work in this area in the buildings sector. So, I would love to see\nnew regulations put in place to make our buildings more energy efficient as a tool for mitigating climate change, as well as healthier.\n\nThis will require specialist skills like mine. From my experience this needs to be regulated. We can not rely on the developers or\narchitects/engineers to make this happen because the majority of people will only do it if they HAVE to. General comments:\nAgriculture needs to be targeted, there needs to be mandatory reporting on GHG emissions and targets by each company, as well as\n\na plan for reaching the targets. Without this, we will not reach our international commitment to the Paris agreement as companies\ntend to do the minimum required."
    }
  ]
}
